<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
>
	<channel>
		<title></title>
		<description>Computational Biology, Neuroscience, Genomics, Transcriptomics, Machine Learning
</description>		
		<sy:updatePeriod>daily</sy:updatePeriod>
		<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
		<link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
		<atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
		
		
            
                <item>
                    <title>NPAS4 regulates the transcriptional response of the suprachiasmatic nucleus to light and circadian behavior</title>
                    
                        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published at Neuron, Oct 2021.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2021.07.026&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2021.07.026&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) is the master circadian pacemaker in
mammals and is entrained by environmental light. However, the molecular basis of the
response of the SCN to light is not fully understood. We used RNA/Chromatin
Immunoprecipitation/single-nucleus sequencing with circadian behavioral assays to
identify mouse SCN cell types and to explore their responses to light. We identified
three peptidergic cell types that responded to light in the SCN: (arginine vasopressin
[AVP], vasoactive intestinal peptide [VIP], and cholecystokinin [CCK]). In each cell type,
light-responsive subgroups were enriched for expression of Neuronal PAS Domain
Protein 4 (NPAS4) target genes. Further, mice lacking Npas4 had a longer circadian
period in constant conditions, a damped phase response curve to light, and reduced
light-induced gene expression in the SCN. Together, our data indicate that NPAS4 is
necessary for normal transcriptional responses to light in the SCN and is critical for
photic phase-shifting of circadian behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                    <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                    <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/20/scn-neuron.html</link>
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/10/20/scn-neuron.html</guid>
                </item>
            
		
            
                <item>
                    <title>Resolving cellular and molecular diversity along the hippocampal anterior-to-posterior axis in humans</title>
                    
                        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published at Neuron, July 2021.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2021.05.003&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.1016/j.neuron.2021.05.003&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hippocampus supports many facets of cognition, including learning, memory, and emotional processing. Anatomically, the hippocampus runs along a longitudinal axis, posterior to anterior in primates. The structure, function, and connectivity of the hippocampus vary along this axis. In human hippocampus, longitudinal functional heterogeneity remains an active area of investigation, and structural heterogeneity has not been described. To understand the cellular and molecular diversity along the hippocampal long axis in human brain and define molecular signatures corresponding to functional domains, we performed single-nuclei RNA sequencing on surgically resected human anterior and posterior hippocampus from epilepsy patients, identifying differentially expressed genes at cellular resolution. We further identify axis- and cell-type-specific gene expression signatures that differentially intersect with human genetic signals, identifying cell-type-specific genes in the posterior hippocampus for cognitive function and the anterior hippocampus for mood and affect. These data are accessible as a public resource through an interactive website.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                    <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/07/hippo-neuron.html</link>
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/07/07/hippo-neuron.html</guid>
                </item>
            
		
            
                <item>
                    <title>Expression of FoxP2 in the Basal Ganglia Regulates Vocal Motor Sequences in the Adult Songbird</title>
                    
                        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published at Nature Communications, May 2021.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-22918-2&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-22918-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disruption of the transcription factor FoxP2, which is enriched in the basal ganglia, impairs vocal development in humans and songbirds. The basal ganglia are important for the selection and sequencing of motor actions, but the circuit mechanisms governing accurate sequencing of learned vocalizations are unknown. Here, we show that expression of FoxP2 in the basal ganglia is vital for the fluent initiation and termination of birdsong, as well as the maintenance of song syllable sequencing in adulthood. Knockdown of FoxP2 imbalances dopamine receptor expression across striatal direct-like and indirect-like pathways, suggesting a role of dopaminergic signaling in regulating vocal motor sequencing. Confirming this prediction, we show that phasic dopamine activation, and not inhibition, during singing drives repetition of song syllables, thus also impairing fluent initiation and termination of birdsong. These findings demonstrate discrete circuit origins for the dysfluent repetition of vocal elements in songbirds, with implications for speech disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                    <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                    <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/11/birdfoxp2-natcom.html</link>
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/05/11/birdfoxp2-natcom.html</guid>
                </item>
            
		
            
                <item>
                    <title>FOXP1 negatively regulates intrinsic excitability in D2 striatal projection neurons by promoting inwardly rectifying and leak potassium currents</title>
                    
                        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published at Molecular Psychiatry, Jan 2021.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41380-020-00995-x&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.1038/s41380-020-00995-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heterozygous loss-of-function mutations in the transcription factor FOXP1 are strongly associated with autism. Dopamine receptor 2 expressing (D2) striatal projection neurons (SPNs) in heterozygous Foxp1 (Foxp1+/-) mice have higher intrinsic excitability. To understand the mechanisms underlying this alteration, we examined SPNs with cell-type specific homozygous Foxp1 deletion to study cell-autonomous regulation by Foxp1. As in Foxp1+/- mice, D2 SPNs had increased intrinsic excitability with homozygous Foxp1 deletion. This effect involved postnatal mechanisms. The hyperexcitability was mainly due to down-regulation of two classes of potassium currents: inwardly rectifying (KIR) and leak (KLeak). Single-cell RNA sequencing data from D2 SPNs with Foxp1 deletion indicated the down-regulation of transcripts of candidate ion channels that may underlie these currents: Kcnj2 and Kcnj4 for KIR and Kcnk2 for KLeak. This Foxp1-dependent regulation was neuron-type specific since these same currents and transcripts were either unchanged, or very little changed, in D1 SPNs with cell-specific Foxp1 deletion. Our data are consistent with a model where FOXP1 negatively regulates the excitability of D2 SPNs through KIR and KLeak by transcriptionally activating their corresponding transcripts. This, in turn, provides a novel example of how a transcription factor may regulate multiple genes to impact neuronal electrophysiological function that depends on the integration of multiple current types - and do this in a cell-specific fashion. Our findings provide initial clues to altered neuronal function and possible therapeutic strategies not only for FOXP1-associated autism but also for other autism forms associated with transcription factor dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                    <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/05/foxp1d2spn-molpsy.html</link>
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/01/05/foxp1d2spn-molpsy.html</guid>
                </item>
            
		
            
                <item>
                    <title>An essential role for MEF2C in the cortical response to loss of sleep in mice</title>
                    
                        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published at eLife, Aug 2020.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.58331&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.7554/eLife.58331&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuronal activity and gene expression in response to the loss of sleep can
provide a window into the enigma of sleep function. Sleep loss is associated
with brain differential gene expression, an increase in pyramidal cell mEPSC
frequency and amplitude, and a characteristic rebound and resolution of slow
wave sleep-slow wave activity (SWS-SWA). However, the molecular mechanism(s)
mediating the sleep loss response are not well understood. We show that
sleep-loss regulates MEF2C phosphorylation, a key mechanism regulating MEF2C
transcriptional activity, and that MEF2C function in postnatal excitatory
forebrain neurons is required for the biological events in response to sleep
loss in C57BL/6J mice. These include altered gene expression, the increase and
recovery of synaptic strength, and the rebound and resolution of SWS-SWA, which
implicate MEF2C as an essential regulator of sleep function.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                    <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/08/26/sleep-elife.html</link>
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/08/26/sleep-elife.html</guid>
                </item>
            
		
            
                <item>
                    <title>Single-cell analysis of Foxp1-driven mechanisms essential for striatal development</title>
                    
                        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published at Cell Reports, Feb 2020.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2020.02.030&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.1016/j.celrep.2020.02.030&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The striatum is a critical forebrain structure integrating cognitive, sensory,
and motor information from diverse brain regions into meaningful behavioral
output. However, the transcriptional mechanisms underlying striatal development
at single-cell resolution remain unknown. Using single-cell RNA sequencing
(RNA-seq), we examine the cellular diversity of the early postnatal striatum and
show that Foxp1, a transcription factor strongly linked to autism and
intellectual disability, regulates the cellular composition, neurochemical
architecture, and connectivity of the striatum in a cell-type-dependent fashion.
We also identify Foxp1-regulated target genes within distinct cell types and
connect these molecular changes to functional and behavioral deficits relevant
to phenotypes described in patients with FOXP1 loss-of-function mutations. Using
this approach, we could also examine the non-cell-autonomous effects produced by
disrupting one cell type and the molecular compensation that occurs in other
populations. These data reveal the cell-type-specific transcriptional mechanisms
regulated by Foxp1 that underlie distinct features of striatal circuitry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                    <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                    <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/03/01/foxp1-cellreports.html</link>
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/03/01/foxp1-cellreports.html</guid>
                </item>
            
		
            
                <item>
                    <title>Cortical Foxp2 Supports Behavioral Flexibility and Developmental Dopamine D1 Receptor Expression</title>
                    
                        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published at Cerebral Cortex, March 2020.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;*&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhz209&quot;&gt; doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhz209&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genetic studies have associated FOXP2 variation with speech and language
disorders and other neurodevelopmental disorders (NDDs) involving pathology of
the cortex. In this brain region, FoxP2 is expressed from development into
adulthood, but little is known about its downstream molecular and behavioral
functions. Here, we characterized cortex-specific Foxp2 conditional knockout
mice and found a major deficit in reversal learning, a form of behavioral
flexibility. In contrast, they showed normal activity levels, anxiety, and
vocalizations, save for a slight decrease in neonatal call loudness. These
behavioral phenotypes were accompanied by decreased cortical dopamine D1
receptor (D1R) expression at neonatal and adult stages, while general cortical
development remained unaffected. Finally, using single-cell transcriptomics, we
identified at least five excitatory and three inhibitory D1R-expressing cell
types in neonatal frontal cortex, and we found changes in D1R cell type
composition and gene expression upon cortical Foxp2 deletion. Strikingly, these
alterations included non-cell-autonomous changes in upper layer neurons and
interneurons. Together, these data support a role for Foxp2 in the development
of dopamine-modulated cortical circuits and behaviors relevant to NDDs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                    <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/11/11/foxp2-cerebralcortex.html</link>
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/11/11/foxp2-cerebralcortex.html</guid>
                </item>
            
		
            
                <item>
                    <title>Beyond bulk - a review of single cell transcriptomics methodologies and applications</title>
                    
                        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Published in Current Opinion in Biotechnology, 2019.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.copbio.2019.03.001&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.1016/j.copbio.2019.03.001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) is a promising approach to study the
transcriptomes of individual cells in the brain and the central nervous system
(CNS). This technology acts as a bridge between neuroscience, computational
biology, and systems biology, enabling an unbiased and novel understanding of
the cellular composition of the brain and CNS. Gene expression at the single
cell resolution is often noisy, sparse, and high-dimensional, creating
challenges for computational analysis of such data. In this review, we overview
fundamental sample preparation and data analysis processes of scRNA-seq and
provide a comparative perspective for analyzing and visualizing these data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
                    <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/04/10/beyondbulk-copbio.html</link>
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/04/10/beyondbulk-copbio.html</guid>
                </item>
            
		
            
                <item>
                    <title>Foxp1 regulation of neonatal vocalizations via cortical development</title>
                    
                        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genes Dev. 2017 Oct 15;31(20):2039-2055. Epub 2017 Nov 14.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1101/gad.305037.117&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.1101/gad.305037.117&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The molecular mechanisms driving brain development at risk in autism spectrum
disorders (ASDs) remain mostly unknown. Previous studies have implicated the
transcription factor FOXP1 in both brain development and ASD pathophysiology.
However, the specific molecular pathways both upstream of and downstream from
FOXP1 are not fully understood. To elucidate the contribution of FOXP1-mediated
signaling to brain development and, in particular, neocortical development, we
generated forebrain-specific Foxp1 conditional knockout mice. We show that
deletion of Foxp1 in the developing forebrain leads to impairments in neonatal
vocalizations as well as neocortical cytoarchitectonic alterations via neuronal
positioning and migration. Using a genomics approach, we identified the
transcriptional networks regulated by Foxp1 in the developing neocortex and
found that such networks are enriched for downstream targets involved in
neurogenesis and neuronal migration. We also uncovered mechanistic insight into
Foxp1 function by demonstrating that sumoylation of Foxp1 during embryonic brain
development is necessary for mediating proper interactions between Foxp1 and the
NuRD complex. Furthermore, we demonstrated that sumoylation of Foxp1 affects
neuronal differentiation and migration in the developing neocortex. Together,
these data provide critical mechanistic insights into the function of FOXP1 in
the developing neocortex and may reveal molecular pathways at risk in ASD.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                    <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/11/14/foxp1cortex-gnd.html</link>
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/11/14/foxp1cortex-gnd.html</guid>
                </item>
            
		
            
                <item>
                    <title>Foxp1 in Forebrain Pyramidal Neurons Controls Gene Expression Required for Spatial Learning and Synaptic Plasticity</title>
                    
                        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;J Neurosci. 2017 Nov 8;37(45):10917-10931. Epub 2017 Oct 4.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1005-17.2017&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1005-17.2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genetic perturbations of the transcription factor Forkhead Box P1 (FOXP1) are
causative for severe forms of autism spectrum disorder that are often comorbid
with intellectual disability. Recent work has begun to reveal an important role
for FoxP1 in brain development, but the brain-region-specific contributions of
Foxp1 to autism and intellectual disability phenotypes have yet to be determined
fully. Here, we describe Foxp1 conditional knock-out (Foxp1cKO) male and female
mice with loss of Foxp1 in the pyramidal neurons of the neocortex and the
CA1/CA2 subfields of the hippocampus. Foxp1cKO mice exhibit behavioral
phenotypes that are of potential relevance to autism spectrum disorder,
including hyperactivity, increased anxiety, communication impairments, and
decreased sociability. In addition, Foxp1cKO mice have gross deficits in
learning and memory tasks of relevance to intellectual disability. Using a
genome-wide approach, we identified differentially expressed genes in the
hippocampus of Foxp1cKO mice associated with synaptic function and development.
Furthermore, using magnetic resonance imaging, we uncovered a significant
reduction in the volumes of both the entire hippocampus as well as individual
hippocampal subfields of Foxp1cKO mice. Finally, we observed reduced maintenance
of LTP in area CA1 of the hippocampus in these mutant mice. Together, these data
suggest that proper expression of Foxp1 in the pyramidal neurons of the
forebrain is important for regulating gene expression pathways that contribute
to specific behaviors reminiscent of those seen in autism and intellectual
disability. In particular, Foxp1 regulation of gene expression appears to be
crucial for normal hippocampal development, CA1 plasticity, and spatial
learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT Loss-of-function mutations in the transcription
factor Forkhead Box P1 (FOXP1) lead to autism spectrum disorder and intellectual
disability. Understanding the potential brain-region-specific contributions of
FOXP1 to disease-relevant phenotypes could be a critical first step in the
management of patients with these mutations. Here, we report that Foxp1
conditional knock-out (Foxp1cKO) mice with loss of Foxp1 in the neocortex and
hippocampus display autism and intellectual-disability-relevant behaviors. We
also show that these phenotypes correlate with changes in both the genomic and
physiological profiles of the hippocampus in Foxp1cKO mice. Our work
demonstrates that brain-region-specific FOXP1 expression may relate to distinct,
clinically relevant phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
                    <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/11/08/foxp1cortex-jneuro.html</link>
                    <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/11/08/foxp1cortex-jneuro.html</guid>
                </item>
            
		
	</channel>
</rss>
